Guide to the Margarett Root Brown College Masters' records, 1965-2004 UA 345
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Margarett Root Brown College Masters' Records
1965-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Brotzen, Franz R.
UA 345
0.75 Linear Feet
This collection consists of materials collected by former Masters of Brown College, Rice University.
Historical Sketch
In 1963 Jones was the only women's college at Rice, and there was such a severe housing shortage that some Rice women were being housed in another university's dorms. In October of that year, George R. Brown and his wife Alice Pratt Brown donated one million dollars through the Brown Foundation to build a new dorm for women at Rice. The new college was established in memory of their sister-in-law, Margarett Root Brown, (1896-1963) who was the wife of the also late Hermann Brown. Margarett Brown was devoted to the fine arts as an art critic and collector and served on the boards of several of organizations. As a tribute to her love of the arts, the first floor of Brown College houses a wide variety of paintings and antique furniture donated by the George R. Brown family and others.
The College was dedicated on October 3, 1965 and was filled primarily by women who had volunteered to leave Jones College to start a new college. Since then other colleges have been added to Rice, and beginning in 1971 some colleges went co-ed. Brown held out as the last all female college until 1987 when it agreed to accept male members.
The College is an eight-story masonry structure on the northeast campus. The high-rise was devised to spare trees. In 2001 new construction will change the Brown College complex. An addition will connect to Brown College on four levels and will extend west of the College in the area occupied by the current Jones Masters' House.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection consists of the records of former Brown College Masters, starting with Franz and Frances Brotzen.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Accruals Note
Additional materials are expected for this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Franz Ridgway Brotzen in 2013.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Residential colleges; Faculty; Social life and customs
Places
Rice University
- Series I: Frank E. and Carol Sue Vandiver, 1965-1966, 174632
  - Correspondence, 1965-1966; 174633 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Donald R. and Janis Baker, 1966-1977, 174634
  - Budget, 1966-1967; 174635 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - College Student Lists, 1972/1973; 183703 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1967, 1971-1972, 1975-1976; 174636 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Master's and President's Committee, 1970-1971; 174637 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series III: Franz and Frances Brotzen, 1977-1982, 173237
  General Note
  The files in this series contain materials collected primarily by Frances Brotzen during her co-mastership and through her role as a Brown College associate.
  - 15th Anniversary, 1980-1981; 183704 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Associates (photographs), 1982-2000; 173238 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1977-2004; 173239 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Events, 1977-1982; 183705 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Freshman Week, 1977-1982; 183706 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Invoices, 1977-1982; 183707 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Masters, 1977-1982; 173240 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newcomer's Handbook, 1981/1982; 183708 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newsclippings, 1978-1999; 173241 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Perkins, Margaret "Meg", 1990; 173242 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rules and Regulations Handbook, 1981/1982; 183709 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student Lists, 1982/1983; 183710 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Summer Plans, 1977/1978; 183711 (Box 2, Folder 11)